<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[Gatsby Starter Blog RSS Feed]]></title><description><![CDATA[A journal for my expermients with coffee]]></description><link>https://coffee.blog.vidyarthi.dev</link><generator>GatsbyJS</generator><lastBuildDate>Sat, 21 Jan 2023 20:02:38 GMT</lastBuildDate><item><title><![CDATA[Cappuccino: The liquid dessert]]></title><description><![CDATA[Before you blast me on the technicalities of espresso and cappuccino, I would confess this is a jugad.
For this jugad Cappuccino recipe we…]]></description><link>https://coffee.blog.vidyarthi.dev/liquid-desert/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://coffee.blog.vidyarthi.dev/liquid-desert/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 21 Jan 2023 05:30:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Before you blast me on the technicalities of espresso and cappuccino, I would confess this is a jugad.
For this jugad Cappuccino recipe we would replace the complicated espresso machine with a humble French press.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have made it multiple times without ever tasting it myself, the refinements are done based on my sister&apos;s kind feedbacks.
After arranging some blind tasting, I feel &quot;instant coffee&quot; would be best for this recipe. You may get decent results with omni roasted coffee beans having the notes of Coco or caramel, however if you are using beans with fruity/citrusy/flowery or malty notes usually the subtle note would not be noticeable or would make the outcome unpleasant. Hence to play safe and reduce the number of required equipment let’s move ahead with the instant coffee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Which Instant Coffee ??&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, I can answer that, once upon a time I had given almost all the instant coffee brands a try. I can safely say the black coffee made out of the tiny instant coffee sachets tastes nastiest. Nescafe gold is ok. Columbia Brew Coffee (Espresso) which comes in resealable black plastic pack is decent, the smaller ones which comes in cardboard boxes are somehow not the same. However, if you would ask me which one would I prefer, I would most probably go with the Davidoff Espresso 57. It is smooth and pleasant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If Davidoff 57 is not accessible, no problems, most of the coffee works ok due to the presence of milk and sugar&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;How much coffee ??&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Umm it depends, I usually put something between 1 teaspoon to 2 teaspoon based on the person who is drinking. If you would prefer to keep the amount of sugar minimal maybe a teaspoon full would be a good starting point. Based on the amount of coffee the amount of sugar will also change less coffee would require lesser amount of sugar. I try to limit sugar from one and a half spoon to 2 spoon, but to be truthful it varies from person to person.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Any tips on milk&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don&apos;t use the toned milk at all, if you have access to local dairy farmer, fresh milk is the best. If not at least opt for the full fat milk. Frothing milk without steam wand is already very complicated let&apos;s not complicate it any further.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The recommend temperature for milk is 60°C hence all efforts should be made to ensure milk should gently simmer on stove and should never boil.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The technique&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Technically speaking Cappuccino is one third espresso, one third milk and one third foam. We are going to replace the one third espresso with the one third strong instant coffee. Which would mean for a 300 ml cup, we are looking for 100ml milk and 100ml water, for a 150 ml cup the milk and water will come down to 50ml each.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Steps&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Take the required amount of boiling water in your cappuccino cup, put the required amount of coffee and sugar into it and stir it thoroughly to completely dissolve the sugar crystals.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Detach the glass body of the French press from its stand and place the glass vessel on a level surface&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is very difficult to froth milk if the volume of milk is less, if the required volume of milk is less than 100 ml, put at least 100ml milk into the French press, we can always put back the unused frothed milk.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Now we need to rapidly move the plunger up and down within the milk placed inside the French press vessel. While doing so we must be mindful of the following facts
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The French press body is made of glass, if we would repeatedly hit the bottom with plunger, it may break hence extreme caution should be observed while moving the plunger&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If we repeatedly break the surface of milk while moving the plunger the bubbles would be bigger in size and we don&apos;t want that, breaking the milk surface a couple of time is ok but we should try to reduce it&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We should maintain the up and down motion of the plunger till the volume of milk is doubled, it may take some time but it is very crucial that the volume of the milk gets doubled.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Once the volume of milk gets doubled transfer it into a sturdy container with a decent spout (Preferably milk pitcher, however any container with handle and decent spout would do). After placing the milk into the container, swirl the container a couple of time and tap it thrice. If using milk pitcher, do not fill the pitcher beyond the 1/3 &lt;sup&gt;rd&lt;/sup&gt; mark, or else the flow would get distorted.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you are successful in frothing the milk you would have equal volume of milk and froth in the frothed milk. Hence now on wherever we would mention the required volume of frothed milk, it would imply double the volume of required milk&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We need to pour the milk in two phases, phase one would create the canvas and phase two would help us to create pattern on the canvas with bright contrast&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For phase one pour half the required volume of frothed milk in the black coffee from about 20 cm height and gently swirl the cup. If the colour tone is not even, gentlly stir the cofee with a spoon&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For phase 2, pour the remaining volume of the frothed milk in the centre of the cup with as little distance as possible. Try to gradually increase the flow rate in the second phase. You would have a decent looking cappuccino if you  would manage to adjust the tilt of the cappuccino cup with pouring of milk, or else you would at least have a decent tasting cup of coffee.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Are there any tricks to improve the outcome of milk frothing&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why not, in 2017 World Barista Championship, Ben Put introduced the concept of freeze distillation. We may use it, all it needs is packaged milk, freeze and time. If you want to improve the foaming of milk place the milk packet in the freezer for 8 hours, remove the frozen milk from freezer, make a small hole in the packet and place it on top of container which may collect the dripping milk. Milk is a mixture of fat, proteins, sugar and water, of which water has the highest melting point. If we use the collected milk when melting is only halfway complete, we would get richer milk which would foam much better. To avoid milk spoilage, it is recommended to ensure the melting setup is placed inside a freeze, which usually stretches the melting to up to 30 hours. Rest the recipe stays same maybe the recipe would require a little lesser sugar that’s all.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[And then there was Coffee]]></title><description><![CDATA[I love the narratives with great origin stories, and now I have decided to dedicate my time to chronicle my journey into the rabbit hole…]]></description><link>https://coffee.blog.vidyarthi.dev/origin-story/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://coffee.blog.vidyarthi.dev/origin-story/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 17 Jan 2023 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;I love the narratives with great origin stories, and now I have decided to dedicate my time to chronicle my journey into the rabbit hole called &quot;Brewed Coffee”, hence I am obliged to include the origin story of this coffee affair&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The timeless verse of the Chef Ranveer Brar 🙏 &quot;Ye v India ki nhi hai&quot; holds true for Coffee also. However for coffee we at least know Baba Budan is to be thanked for blessing us with the joy of brewed delicacy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh, and here&apos;s a short note from Wikipedia on
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Coffee_production_in_India&quot;&gt;Coffee Production in India&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the Indian context, coffee growing started with an Indian Muslim saint, Baba Budan,[2][8] who, while returning from a pilgrimage to Mecca, smuggled seven coffee beans (by hiding them in his beard) from Yemen to Mysore in India.[7] He planted them on the Chandra Drona Giri (1,829 metres (6,001 ft))(&apos;Giri&apos; means &quot;hill&quot;) in Chikkamagaluru district. It was considered an illegal act to take out green coffee seed out of Arabia. As number seven is a sacrosanct number in Islamic religion, the saint&apos;s act of carrying seven coffee beans was considered a religious act&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
      class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-wrapper&quot;
      style=&quot;position: relative; display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; max-width: 630px; &quot;
    &gt;
      &lt;a
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-link&quot;
    href=&quot;/static/2689f2a2da0183f9b604e9d6d65c8557/c08c5/blog-icon.jpg&quot;
    style=&quot;display: block&quot;
    target=&quot;_blank&quot;
    rel=&quot;noopener&quot;
  &gt;
    &lt;span
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-background-image&quot;
    style=&quot;padding-bottom: 49.36708860759494%; position: relative; bottom: 0; left: 0; background-image: url(&apos;data:image/jpeg;base64,/9j/2wBDABALDA4MChAODQ4SERATGCgaGBYWGDEjJR0oOjM9PDkzODdASFxOQERXRTc4UG1RV19iZ2hnPk1xeXBkeFxlZ2P/2wBDARESEhgVGC8aGi9jQjhCY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2P/wgARCAAKABQDASIAAhEBAxEB/8QAGAAAAgMAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAIBAwT/xAAWAQEBAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAADAAH/2gAMAwEAAhADEAAAAcbOppBcW//EABsQAQACAgMAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAEAAgMhMTJB/9oACAEBAAEFAvdCVuzH34lAT//EABURAQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAR/9oACAEDAQE/AUf/xAAUEQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAQ/9oACAECAQE/AT//xAAdEAABBAIDAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAQIRISJRUnGi/9oACAEBAAY/AsqnZeZTvYvY6ORaH//EABwQAAMBAAIDAAAAAAAAAAAAAAERIQAxQXGxwf/aAAgBAQABPyFh1rSzOJCLMO/uAdWUM0L7yAIXCeMAoKl3/9oADAMBAAIAAwAAABBf7//EABURAQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABAR/9oACAEDAQE/EIP/xAAVEQEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAEf/aAAgBAgEBPxCq/8QAHBABAAICAwEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAREhAEExUWGB/9oACAEBAAE/EAGblKA7IgApY5xISgJUp2mq9TJ7AVChv0xr1AgbAbH3EqXURWmK0CBCYIKz/9k=&apos;); background-size: cover; display: block;&quot;
  &gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;img
        class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-image&quot;
        alt=&quot;Coffee&quot;
        title=&quot;&quot;
        src=&quot;/static/2689f2a2da0183f9b604e9d6d65c8557/828fb/blog-icon.jpg&quot;
        srcset=&quot;/static/2689f2a2da0183f9b604e9d6d65c8557/ff44c/blog-icon.jpg 158w,
/static/2689f2a2da0183f9b604e9d6d65c8557/a6688/blog-icon.jpg 315w,
/static/2689f2a2da0183f9b604e9d6d65c8557/828fb/blog-icon.jpg 630w,
/static/2689f2a2da0183f9b604e9d6d65c8557/c08c5/blog-icon.jpg 640w&quot;
        sizes=&quot;(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px&quot;
        style=&quot;width:100%;height:100%;margin:0;vertical-align:middle;position:absolute;top:0;left:0;&quot;
        loading=&quot;lazy&quot;
        decoding=&quot;async&quot;
      /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A religious act indeed !!! my wallet could never afford imported Ethiopian Yirgacheffe had he not smuggled the seven little beans of joy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enough on the origins of coffee in India now it is time to delve into why I willingly put so much effort into perfecting this psychoactive brew.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well on a fine Winter afternoon a couple of years back I was strolling across the isles of a retail store when I came across a black packet of freshly put instant Coffee, I was reading through the back label when I saw the magical lines &quot;Research has shown coffee reduces the risk of Alzheimer&apos;s disease&quot;. I was shell shocked; the disease I dread most, the Voldemort of the diseases and I can reduce the risk with just a cup of coffee. Why not??&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I instantly purchased the pack of instant coffee. I had tasted coffee earlier, however all those earlier instances involved copious amount of sugar in a cup of milk and cautious addition of half a spoon of coffee to ensure the concoction never ever turns bitter. No playing around with the amount of sugar at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is no fooling around the fact the more I am aging quirkier I am becoming. At the point when I decided to try black coffee I had already decided to reduce the amount of crystal sugar and my divorce with milk in its pure liquid form was already formalized. Hence I did what I could, I dissolved a spoon of that brown instant coffee into hot unsweetened water. I knew the stuff would not taste great but never knew it would be stuff of nightmares !!!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the period I tried to vary the ratio of that bitter brown powder and the hot water and even the temperature of the water, frankly nothing worked. To put it politely may be I am over sensitive to the bitter taste. I had decided to call quits on coffee when Youtube recommended a video of his holiness 🙏 Shree Shree 108 the Barista of Baristas Mr James Hoffman. He was describing brewed coffee as sweet. I thought maybe this instant coffee is the &quot;goldana chai&quot; scam of the coffee world, maybe I need the brewed coffee. And friend that is &quot;How I met brewed coffee&quot;. The decision to pursue the brewed coffee took me down the rabbit hole which finally materialized into this tell all series. I hope some of the future blogs will have some stuff which may help you with your own journey.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item></channel></rss>