<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[Gatsby Starter Blog RSS Feed]]></title><description><![CDATA[A journal for my expermients with coffee]]></description><link>https://coffee.blog.vidyarthi.dev</link><generator>GatsbyJS</generator><lastBuildDate>Tue, 17 Jan 2023 17:06:49 GMT</lastBuildDate><item><title><![CDATA[And then there was Coffee]]></title><description><![CDATA[I love the narratives with great origin stories, and now I have decided to dedicate my time to chronicle my journey into the rabbit hole…]]></description><link>https://coffee.blog.vidyarthi.dev/origin-story/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://coffee.blog.vidyarthi.dev/origin-story/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 17 Jan 2023 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;I love the narratives with great origin stories, and now I have decided to dedicate my time to chronicle my journey into the rabbit hole called &quot;Brewed Coffee”, hence I am obliged to include the origin story of this coffee affair&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The timeless verse of the Chef Ranveer Brar 🙏 &quot;Ye v India ki nhi hai&quot; holds true for Coffee also. However for coffee we at least know Baba Budan is to be thanked for blessing us with the joy of brewed delicacy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh, and here&apos;s a short note from Wikipedia on
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Coffee_production_in_India&quot;&gt;Coffee Production in India&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the Indian context, coffee growing started with an Indian Muslim saint, Baba Budan,[2][8] who, while returning from a pilgrimage to Mecca, smuggled seven coffee beans (by hiding them in his beard) from Yemen to Mysore in India.[7] He planted them on the Chandra Drona Giri (1,829 metres (6,001 ft))(&apos;Giri&apos; means &quot;hill&quot;) in Chikkamagaluru district. It was considered an illegal act to take out green coffee seed out of Arabia. As number seven is a sacrosanct number in Islamic religion, the saint&apos;s act of carrying seven coffee beans was considered a religious act&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
      class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-wrapper&quot;
      style=&quot;position: relative; display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; max-width: 630px; &quot;
    &gt;
      &lt;a
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-link&quot;
    href=&quot;/coffe-blog/static/2689f2a2da0183f9b604e9d6d65c8557/c08c5/blog-icon.jpg&quot;
    style=&quot;display: block&quot;
    target=&quot;_blank&quot;
    rel=&quot;noopener&quot;
  &gt;
    &lt;span
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-background-image&quot;
    style=&quot;padding-bottom: 49.36708860759494%; position: relative; bottom: 0; left: 0; background-image: url(&apos;data:image/jpeg;base64,/9j/2wBDABALDA4MChAODQ4SERATGCgaGBYWGDEjJR0oOjM9PDkzODdASFxOQERXRTc4UG1RV19iZ2hnPk1xeXBkeFxlZ2P/2wBDARESEhgVGC8aGi9jQjhCY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2P/wgARCAAKABQDASIAAhEBAxEB/8QAGAAAAgMAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAIBAwT/xAAWAQEBAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAADAAH/2gAMAwEAAhADEAAAAcbOppBcW//EABsQAQACAgMAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAEAAgMhMTJB/9oACAEBAAEFAvdCVuzH34lAT//EABURAQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAR/9oACAEDAQE/AUf/xAAUEQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAQ/9oACAECAQE/AT//xAAdEAABBAIDAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAQIRISJRUnGi/9oACAEBAAY/AsqnZeZTvYvY6ORaH//EABwQAAMBAAIDAAAAAAAAAAAAAAERIQAxQXGxwf/aAAgBAQABPyFh1rSzOJCLMO/uAdWUM0L7yAIXCeMAoKl3/9oADAMBAAIAAwAAABBf7//EABURAQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABAR/9oACAEDAQE/EIP/xAAVEQEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAEf/aAAgBAgEBPxCq/8QAHBABAAICAwEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAREhAEExUWGB/9oACAEBAAE/EAGblKA7IgApY5xISgJUp2mq9TJ7AVChv0xr1AgbAbH3EqXURWmK0CBCYIKz/9k=&apos;); background-size: cover; display: block;&quot;
  &gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;img
        class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-image&quot;
        alt=&quot;Coffee&quot;
        title=&quot;&quot;
        src=&quot;/coffe-blog/static/2689f2a2da0183f9b604e9d6d65c8557/828fb/blog-icon.jpg&quot;
        srcset=&quot;/coffe-blog/static/2689f2a2da0183f9b604e9d6d65c8557/ff44c/blog-icon.jpg 158w,
/coffe-blog/static/2689f2a2da0183f9b604e9d6d65c8557/a6688/blog-icon.jpg 315w,
/coffe-blog/static/2689f2a2da0183f9b604e9d6d65c8557/828fb/blog-icon.jpg 630w,
/coffe-blog/static/2689f2a2da0183f9b604e9d6d65c8557/c08c5/blog-icon.jpg 640w&quot;
        sizes=&quot;(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px&quot;
        style=&quot;width:100%;height:100%;margin:0;vertical-align:middle;position:absolute;top:0;left:0;&quot;
        loading=&quot;lazy&quot;
        decoding=&quot;async&quot;
      /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A religious act indeed !!! my wallet could never afford imported Ethiopian Yirgacheffe had he not smuggled the seven little beans of joy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enough on the origins of coffee in India now it is time to delve into why I willingly put so much effort into perfecting this psychoactive brew.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well on a fine Winter afternoon a couple of years back I was strolling across the isles of a retail store when I came across a black packet of freshly put instant Coffee, I was reading through the back label when I saw the magical lines &quot;Research has shown coffee reduces the risk of Alzheimer&apos;s disease&quot;. I was shell shocked; the disease I dread most, the Voldemort of the diseases and I can reduce the risk with just a cup of coffee. Why not??&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I instantly purchased the pack of instant coffee. I had tasted coffee earlier, however all those earlier instances involved copious amount of sugar in a cup of milk and cautious addition of half a spoon of coffee to ensure the concoction never ever turns bitter. No playing around with the amount of sugar at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is no fooling around the fact the more I am aging quirkier I am becoming. At the point when I decided to try black coffee I had already decided to reduce the amount of crystal sugar and my divorce with milk in its pure liquid form was already formalized. Hence I did what I could I dissolved a spoon of that brown instant coffee into hot unsweetened water. I knew the stuff would not taste great but never knew it would be stuff of nightmares !!!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the period I tried to vary the ratio of that bitter brown powder and the hot water and even the temperature of the water, frankly nothing worked. To put it politely may be I am over sensitive to the bitter taste. I had decided to call quits on coffee when Youtube recommended a video of his holiness 🙏 Shree Shree 108 the Barista of Baristas Mr James Hoffman. He was describing brewed coffee as sweet. I thought maybe this instant coffee is the &quot;goldana chai&quot; scam of the coffee world, maybe I need the brewed coffee. And friend that is &quot;How I met brewed coffee&quot;. The decision to pursue the brewed coffee took me down the rabbit hole which finally materialized into this tell all series. I hope some of the future blogs will have some stuff which may help you with your own journey.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item></channel></rss>